Congratulations, Mr. Pedanski.
Our next guest.
It's okay. Give him a Give him a round
of applause.
Sorry, it's right there. I apologize.
Our next inductee this evening
is Catherine Jorgenson McCutchan.
Another fun fact,
she is the first Norwegian to be
inducted to the Cleveland International
Hall of Fame.
To induct her this evening is someone
who also knows her very well, her
daughter, Karen McCutchan.
Hi.
My name's Karen McCutchan, and today
it's my honor to introduce my mother,
Catherine Jorgenson McCutchan.
You can read all about her many
accomplishments,
contributions to the international
community here in Cleveland,
and her impact on young people in
Cleveland.
Um so, instead I'm going to share just
one story of many stories that people
could say about my mother, Kathy.
It's short, I promise.
Catherine McCutchan was a teacher at
Lakewood High School for many years.
At one point, she had a recently
immigrated student from Romania.
At a time when no one was getting out of
Romania.
So, that was probably a harrowing
journey.
This girl had her heart set on going to
the University of Rochester,
but she had received no funding or
scholarships as a new immigrant.
Her father, who had a doctorate in
engineering
from Romania,
was working as a janitor here in
Cleveland.
So, there was no money
uh
to cover college tuition from the
family.
Kathy spent two full days on the phone
with the admissions committee at
University of Rochester.
I don't know what kind of arm twisting
she was doing.
But after those two days, that student
had a full ride for 4 years to the
University of Rochester.
>> [applause]
>> And her father had a job offer.
To this day,
this family still does not know
how all this came to be.
Ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to
introduce you to Katherine McCutcheon.
>> [applause]
[applause]
>> This is quite an honor.
I
do not
I do not have no region accent.
The reason is I'm second generation.
And second generation people
seldom get recognized to represent all
those who preceded them.
I am here for that reason.
First of all,
in my field,
I felt that everyone needs
to have a little bit of action with
their body so that their attention span
is sustained. So, I suggest that you
stand up, give yourself a little wiggle,
give your body a little shake,
and be prepared for two additional
speakers.
>> [applause and cheering]
>> What are the Norwegian characteristics?
I've been told that they are stoic. That
means they do not
desire
sympathy.
They are reserved.
They are modest.
They are polite.
I was admonished
to never, ever, ever toot your own horn.
So, today I would like you to lift your
glass
and give a hip, hip, hooray for the
Norwegians because this is our moment.
What did the Norwegians contribute to
Cleveland?
All of you must know that there is a
very strong
marine
maritime heritage.
It's pretty obvious
that all of you
had ancestors or yourselves who had to
cross the water.
the pond either by air
or by ship.
Well, Norwegians broke the ice with that
aspect of
exploration
because we now know
conclusively that Leif Ericson in the
year 1000 to 1003 established the first
settlement in Newfoundland
calling it Vinland.
You probably have already heard
about Roald Amundsen
Fridtjof Nansen
and maybe even Thor Heyerdahl
who
proved
that uh
probably the Kon-Tiki proved that it was
possible to trans
trans uh to establish a settlement in
the new world.
How does this convey to Cleveland?
I want you to know that the majority of
Norwegians were here
before we were born.
Um
19 1890s
18 and turn of the century was a period
of time when most of the Norwegians
came.
That's where my family came from.
Many of them had a common name.
You might know it from the movie
Frozen
where the snowman was named Olaf.
Well, my father's name was Olaf.
My grandfather's name was Olaf, and my
great-grandfather's name was Olaf, and I
went to St. Olaf College.
>> [clears throat]
>> Um
Those Norwegian men that came
worked primarily as the workforce on the
Great Lakes.
Great Lakes shipping was at its birth.
The steel industry, the manufacturing of
steel,
uh iron ore transport, freighters.
One of them later
was one that I viewed often
from my window.
How could that be?
The William G. Mather
was docked at the end of my street.
In another direction, the Terminal Tower
was from the balcony of my apartment.
This is crazy. I am Cleveland born.
I am Cleveland educated
at a time when the Cleveland schools
were the model of the whole nation.
>> [clears throat]
>> I grew up attending
Kentucky Elementary School, William H.
Brett Junior High
School, and West
Tech High School.
Those teachers and those
methods of teaching us were profound.
They were wonderful teachers, and I'm
very proud.
But why would the Mather be at the
bottom of my street?
My story is personal.
I am a war baby.
I did not know my father.
My father flew
the airplane
the fighter pilot five fighter jet cop
airplane that's on display at the
Western Reserve Historical Society. It
was a P-51 Mustang. Every time I go
there, I feel like I'm reaching out to
him.
So, my mother was a widow.
Later, my mother was a widow twice.
It thrust us into a
condition
that is not
conventional.
We grew up at Lake View Terrace
Apartments.
And as you came to this location
tonight,
they were on your
left side
with a thousand different apartments.
We grew up on welfare.
But in the school,
middle school, I was so aware
of everything happening
resulting from World War II.
Four grandparents, beautiful accents,
were like music to my ears.
They were wonderful, and they were very
kind and generous to us, and it's the
reason we were able to avoid
arrest.
>> [clears throat]
>> Coming from the projects,
that's an achievement.
Um
My classmates included some girls.
Two of them I'd like to tell you about.
One of them was Inara Johannes.
She was laughing.
We sat across from each other at the
lunch table.
And
she was eating an apple.
But I told her, "Inara, you're not
supposed to eat the core of the apple.
You're not supposed to eat the seeds of
the apple."
"Oh, Cathy, you don't understand when
you've been in a concentration camp how
grateful you are for every morsel of
food."
I became sensitive to what was happening
to others
that were of my own age.
Diana Townji
invited me to her house.
I didn't know that people ate rice every
day,
but her family did.
She was Her family had been relocated
from California to Oklahoma
after World War or during World War II.
These people, who were my classmates,
all of us are accidentally born in the
place where we are born.
But all of us are part of humanity.
I think there is no
way that I can say
thank you more
for this wonderful opportunity
to recognize the very slim
number of Norwegians that exist in
Cleveland,
but to give them a tribute to those who
were before us and those that will come
after us.
And thank you so much
for honoring me.
>> [applause]
[applause]
>> Norwegians are polite.
They have three methods of saying thank
you.
The first one is the word takk.
T a k k.
The second one is
mange takk.
Many thanks.
And the third one is
mange tusen takk.
So, mange tusen takk. Many thousand
thanks.
>> [applause]